Francis Millet Rogers Research Material Regarding Francis Davis Millet
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Francis Millet Rogers research material regarding Francis Davis Millet
1897-1955 (bulk 1945-1955)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Francis Millet Rogers
0.4 linear feet
The Francis Millet Rogers research material regarding Francis Davis Millet measures 0.4 linear feet and is dated 1897-1955, with the bulk of the records dated 1945-1955. The collection consists of the manuscript of Rogers' unpublished biography, "Frank D. Millet: American of the Americans," circa 1955, with related correspondence, reference notes, printed matter, and photographs.
Biographical Note
Mr. and Mrs. Rogers decided to give their son, Frances Rogers, the middle name of Millet to honor the artist Francis Davis Millet. The Rogers were friends with the artist's brother, Charles Sumner Millet. Francis Millet Rogers became a scholar of Portuguese language and history who was a member of the romance languages and literature faculty at Harvard University, where he later served as Dean. Between 1945 and 1955, he researched the life and works of the man for whom he was named. Professor Rogers' manuscript, "Frank D. Rogers: American of the Americans," remains unpublished.
Scope and Content Note
The Francis Millet Rogers research material regarding Francis Davis Millet measures 0.4 linear feet and is dated 1897-1955, with the bulk of the records dated 1945-1955. The collection consists of the manuscript of Rogers' unpublished biography, "Frank D. Millet: American of the Americans," circa 1955, with related correspondence, reference notes, printed matter, and photographs.
Related Material
The Archives also holds the papers of Francis Davis Millet and the Millet Family.
Separated Material
Printed material concerning various institutions with which Millet was affiliated, and clippings about F. D. Millet that highlight commissions, his affiliation with the American Academy in Rome, and the Titanic tragedy, were filmed on reel 1096 but are not listed here as the originals were transferred to Smithsonian Libraries in November 1976.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Millet, Francis Davis, 1846-1912
Subjects-Topical:
Muralists -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs
Provenance
Gift of Francis Millet Rogers, 1975. After microfilming in 1976, some of the printed matter was transferred to the Smithsonian Libraries.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 1095-1096 in Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Francis Millet Rogers Research Material Regarding Francis Davis Millet, 1897-1955, Series 1:; (0.4 linear ft.; Box 1; Reels 1095-1096)
  Correspondence includes letters to the Bank of Pittsburgh, 1897-1910, from a shipping agent and F. D. Millet concerning their lunette that will be arriving from England, and receipt of a medal sent to Millet later. Most likely, Dr. Rogers obtained these items from the bank during the course of his research. Research correspondence of Francis Millet Rogers with various individuals and institutions, 1945-1955, concerns the life and works of F. D. Millet.
  The Reference Notes File, originally in a loose leaf notebook, contains sections titled "F/.D.M.'s paintings (easel)," "F.D.M.'s paintings (mural)," "miscellaneous productions," and "source materials." Also included are two small stacks of index cards recording bibliographic citations and miscellaneous notes.
  Reproductions of Millet's Work includes brochures with photographic reproductions and catalogs containing only descriptive text. A booklet titled "The Minnesota Capitol" (frames 384-386) was not in the folder when examined in 2003; it is not known if this item was among the printed material from this collection that went to Smithsonian Libraries in 1976, or if it was removed at a later date (see "Separated Material").
  Photographs include undated copy prints; a few items are printed reproductions of photographs. Included are a bas relief portrait of Francis Davis Millet by Saint Gaudens, 1879, and photographs of Millet by Davis and Sanford, N.Y., circa 1910. There are several photographs of Millet's easel paintings and murals, as well as exterior views of New Jersey courthouses for which murals were commissioned. In addition, there are photographs of a monument to victims of the Titanic and views of a monument to Francis Davis Millet and Archibald Willingham Butt in Washington, D. C. Also included are a "Millet lamp post" in Washington, D.C, a reproduction of the façade of the Octagon, Washington, D. C., and photographs of various medals designed by Millet.
  - Biographical Information about Francis Davis Millet, 1912-1939 (Box 1, Reel 1095)
  - Letters, 1897, 1910 (Box 1, Reel 1095)
  - Research Correspondence, 1945-1955 (Box 1, Reel 1095)
  - Reference Notes File, circa 1945-1946 (Box 1, Reel 1096)
  - Note Cards, circa 1945-1955 (Box 1, Reel 1096)
  - Manuscript, "Frank D. Millet: American of the Americans," circa 1955 (Box 1, Reel 1096)
  - Reproductions of Millet's Work, 1899-1938 (Box 1, Reel 1096)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Reel 1096)
  - (Box 1, Reel 1096)